A Guide to the Paula Treder Architectural Collection, 1969-1972
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Paula Treder Architectural Collection 1969-1972
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2005-002
2.0 cu. ft. 2 boxes; 4 oversize folders
Paula Treder operated her own architectural firm in South Carolina. This collection contains selected professional papers from her projects, including drawings, photographs, and project documents related to Treder's professional and design activities.
Treder, Paula
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The creator donated the Paula Treder Architectural Collection to the International Archive of Woman in Architecture in 2002 and 2005.
Biographical Information
Paula Treder was born in Rockford, Illinois. She received a bachelor of science in architecture (1951) and a master of science in architecture (1953) from the University of Illinois at Champaign-Urbana. Treder worked in a variety of firms throughout the United States before moving to Rock Hill, South Carolina in 1964 and establishing an architectural firm under her own name.
From 1958-1960, Treder wrote on all aspects of housing design and construction including a large number of cover stories on residential design for House & Home where she was an associate editor. She moved to the Wall Street investment banking firm of Drexel Burnham Lambert, in 1972, where she developed an in-house facilities management office of 100+ professional and other staff responsible for the design, furnishing, construction supervision and maintenance of several hundred thousand square feet of office spaces for the firm in New York City, London, and throughout the Uninted States. Treder retired from DBL in 1988, as Director of Facilities Management and as a corporate officer with the title of First Vice President.
Treder is an Emeritus member of AIA (The American Institute of Architects.) She was instrumental in forming the Vancouver, WA chapeter of the AIA and served on the publications and women's committees of the New York chapter and the magazine committee of the South Carolina chapter. Treder was also involved in the Women's Equity Action League (WEAL) during the 1970s and held national and local offices.
She later moved to Tucson, Arizona.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of professional materials created by Paula Treder from 1953 to 2005. The projects include both original and renovation projects at Winthrop College in Rock Hill, South Carolina, an addition to the Fort Mill Public Library and the Rock Hill Fire Station and a few residences. The architectural drawings and a few blueprints of the consultant's drawings are available for all of the projects except the residential projects. The project documents contain her correspondence, contract papers, receipts, product catalogues and site photographs. There are a few newspaper articles related to her projects.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series Personal Papers, Professional Papers, and Project Records. The documents are stored in boxes with the contents of each folder arranged chronologically. The architectural and consultant's shop drawings are organized by project in the oversize folders.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Architectural drawing--20th century.; Women-owned architectural firms.; International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA)
Genre and Form Terms:
Architectural drawings.
Occupations:
Architects.
Contents List
- Personal Papers, 1953 and undated
  - Schoolwork,1953 and undated (Box-folder 2-8, Box-folder 2-7)
- Professional Papers, 1954-2005
  - Biographical Information,2005 (Box-folder 2-9)
  - Clippings,1967, 1970 (Box-folder 2-10)
  - House + Home,1959-1960 (Box-folder 2-11)
  - Professional Correspondence,1958-1988 (Box-folder 2-12)
  - State Architecture Certifications,1954, 1964 (Box-folder 2-13)
  - Volunteer Work,1976-1996 (Box-folder 2-14)
- Project Records, 1969-1972
  - Winthrop College, Rock Hill, South Carolina
    - Job No. 6815, Rutledge Building,1969-1970 (Box-folder 1-1)
    - Job No. 7001, Withers Building,1972 (Box-folder 1-2)
    - Architectural and Shop Drawings,1969-1972, 38 Tracings and 5 Blueprints (Oversize Folder 1)
  - Fire Station, Rock Hill, South Carolina
    - Budgeting and Contract Documents,1970-1971 (Box-folder 1-3)
    - Correspondence and Approved Products,1970-1971 (Box-folder 1-4)
    - Architectural and Shop Drawings,1970-1971, 14 Tracings and 10 Blueprints (Oversize Folder 2)
  - Fort Mill Public Library, South Carolina
    - Building Program and Specifications1970-1972 (Box-folder 1-5)
    - Correspondence (Architect and Client),1970-1972 (Box-folder 1-6)
    - Documents Related to Sherman Construction Co. Inc.,1970-1972 (Box-folder 1-7)
    - Interior Works,1969-1970 (Box-folder 2-1)
    - Approved Products,1970-1972 (Box-folder 2-2)
    - Approved Products and Correspondence,1970-1972 (Box-folder 2-3)
    - Transmittals for Drawings in Oversize Folders,1970-1972 (Box-folder 2-4)
    - Architectural and Shop Drawings,1970-1972, 17 Tracings and 37 Blueprints (Oversize Folder 4)
  - Other Projects
    - Inactive Residential Project Correspondence,1960 and undated (Box-folder 2-5)
    - Project Photographs, misc.,undated (Box-folder 2-6)
    - Residences and Other Projects, Architectural Drawings, 65 Tracings (Oversize Folder 3)